Register of the Frank Dorn Papers, 1927-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Frank Dorn Papers
1927-1976
84007
Hoover Institution Archives
9 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (3.8 linear feet)
Memoirs, correspondence, writings, memoranda, orders, and photographs, relating to General Joseph W. Stilwell, American military operations in the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II, and ethnology in the Philippines.
Dorn, Frank.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1901, June 25 Born, San Francisco, California
1912-1915 Studied violin
1915-1918 Student, San Francisco Insitute of Art
1923 Graduate, U.S. Military Academy, West Point
1926 Assigned to Philippine Islands
1935 Author, Forest Twilight
1936-1938 Military Attache's Office, Peking, China
1939 Promoted to Major
1939-1945 Aide and Public Information Officer for General Joseph Stilwell, 7th Division, III Corps, Headquarters China-Burma-India
1942 Promoted to Colonel
1944 Promoted to Brigadier General
1946-1949 Assistant Commandant and Acting Commandant, Army Information School and Armed Forces Information School, Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania
1950-1951 Office of the Chief of Information, Department of the Army
1953 Retirement Author, The Dorn Cookbook
1954-1957 Exhibits of paintings of Frank Dorn in: California; Galerie Andre Weil, Paris; Instituto de Cultura Hispanica, Madrid; Instituto Mexicano-Norteamericano de Relaciones Culturales, Mexico City
1958 Author, Just A Pinch
Scope and Contents note
Memoirs, correspondence, writings, memoranda, orders, and photographs, relating to General Joseph W. Stilwell, American military operations in the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II, and ethnology in the Philippines.
Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946.; China.; Ethnology--Philippines.; Philippines.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States. Army--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1927-1954 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical sketches, orders and memoranda related to the career of Frank Dorn, arranged chronologically.
  - Awards, commendations, 1927-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical sketches of Frank Dorn (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Orders and memoranda related to the career of Frank Dorn, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1928-1954 (Box 1)
  Arranged by name of correspondent.
  - General
    - Letters of commendation, 1928-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters on retirement, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Altieri, J.J., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barrett, David D., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ch'en Ch'eng, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hsiao I-hsu, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kirby, Lillian, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Li Mi, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Park, F.L., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pizer, Vernon, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Radus (?), Harvey, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ridgway, Matthew B., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stilwell, Joseph W., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sun Li-jen, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Welk, Robert, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Young, Jack, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- China-Burma-India Theater, 1941-1946 (Box 1-2)
  Memoranda, correspondence, reports, and maps, arranged chronologically.
  - Memoranda, reports, correspondence (arranged chronologically)
    - Butler, Harold (British Minister, Washington, D.C.) Directive, "Publicity Requirements for the War in Asia" (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Chinese Eighth Army, Report on the Sung-Shan Campaign, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Loss of Burma" (may have been written for the History of the China-Burma-India Theater, prepared by Gen. Stilwell's staff for the Department of War, This chapter undated., 1944) (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
    - "Status of the Chinese Troops in Yunnan", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Stilwell, Maj. Gen. Joseph W. Orders from Assistant Chief of Staff, Washington, D.C., January 1, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - ANAKIM Project. General Plan, May 19, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Dorn, Col. Frank. Memorandum to Gen. Yu Ta-wei, August 17, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Condon, Col. Reynolds to Chief of Staff, Y-Force, Kunming. "Will the Chinese Fight?" (two copies, page 3 of copy 2 is missing), December 31, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank to the Commanding General, Headquarters, USAF in CBI. "Will the Chinese Fight?", l944, January 4 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Personal Opinion of the Chinese Army to the Commanding General, USAF in CBI from Headquarters, Y-Force Operations Staff, March 21, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Commanding General, USAF, CBI. Memorandum from Headquarters, Y-Task Force, May 9, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Col. Sandusky (copy to be transmitted immediately on receipt to Gen. Claire Chennault), May 9, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Gen. Hsiao I-Hsu, May 18, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Notes and personal comments (typescript), May 10 to July 2, [1944] (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Enslow, Col. Philip H. Letter to Middleton with notes of a conversation with General Lu Han, May 19, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, May 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Letter to Col. Philip Enslow, May 28, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Davies, John (?) Letter to Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, June 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Chief of Staff, Forward Echelon, HQ USAF, CBI, July 11, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Ch'en Ch'eng, Gen. Telegram to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, July 20, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Letter to Gen. Ho Ying-chin (two copies with letter of attached), August 4, 1944, July 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Gen. Hsiao I-Hsu, August 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Condon, Reynolds. Memorandum to Chief of Staff, Y-Force Operations Staff on General Lu Tzu. Reply from Frank Dorn attached (page one is missing), September 11, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell on the Chinese Commanders in the Chinese Expeditionary Forces, September 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Service, John S. Report to Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell entitled "The Need for Greater Realism in Our Relations with Chiang Kai-shek", October 10, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Stilwell, Gen. Joseph W. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, October 20, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Chung Shan-ching. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, October 22, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - "Reconstruction of the Burma Road", Y-Force Operations Staff, October 24, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Press report on the recall of Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, November 3, [1944] (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Davies, John P. "The Chinese Communists and the Great Powers", November 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Davies, John P. "How Red Are the Chinese Communists?", November 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Davies, John P. "Will the Communists Take Over China?", November 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Davies, John P. (?) Letter to Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, November 21, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Historical Report of Y-Force Operations Staff, period thru 24 October 1944, for the Adjutant General, Washington, D.C., November 25, 1944, 1 January 1944 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Davies, John P. "Comments on the Current Crisis", December 5, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Davies, John P. "Reported Central Government Order to Attack New Fourth Army", December 9, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Davies, John P. "The Generalissimo's Dilemmas", December 9, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Training of Chinese Units", December 19, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Taylor, Col. B.F. Memorandum to Frank Dorn, December 20, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Davies, John P. "Increased Political Activity of Dr. Sun Fo", December 26, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Davies, John P. "Visit to Yenan, ", December 27, 1944, December 15-17 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - McClure, Maj. Gen. Robert. Memorandum to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, "Reorganization of Chinese Training and Combat Command", December 17, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Letter to Maj. Gen. Albert C. Wedemeyer, December 28 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Commanding General, U.S.F.C.T., December 31, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Letter to the Japanese People", ca. 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Report to the Adjutant General, Washington, D.C. "Historical Report of Chinese Training and Combat Command (Y-Force Operations Staff and Z-Force), period thru 31 December 1944", January 1, 1944 (sic)[1945], 25 October 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Wedemeyer, Maj. Gen. Albert C. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, January 3, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Wei Li-huang. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, January 15, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Tu Li-ming. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, January 15, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Wedemeyer, Maj. Gen. Albert C. Efficiency Report on General Officer to the Adjutant General, Washington, D.C., January 25, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chieh Han-chien. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, January 30, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Huang Chieh. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, February 2, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Completion of the Salween Campaign", compiled and distributed by Public Relations Officer, Chinese combat command, February 4, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Hsiao Yi-shu. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, April 29, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Report to the Adjutant General, Washington, D.C., July 16, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Li Hua-ying. Letter to Brig. Gen. Frank Dorn, December 19, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Dorn, Brig. Gen. Frank. Memorandum to Lt. Col. Charles H. Franklin, on Y-Force, May 18, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Record of Burma Operations" (second supplement), issued by The First Demobilization Bureau, October 1946 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Map of the Burma Road,; Chinese map, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Japanese flag presented to Frank Dorn by Gen. Li-whang (sic) Wei, December 1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Speeches and Writings, 1929-ca. 1976 (Box 2-6)
  Manuscripts, notes, drafts of writings of Frank Dorn. Arranged chronologically.
  - "An Teh Hai (Palace Eunuch)", l typescript, l carbon copy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Ceremony at Huang Chi Tien for the Lying in State of a Dead Emperor", typescript with drawing, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Li Lien Ying (Life Story from the Imperial Archives in the Forbidden City)", typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Life in the Imperial Palace, and the Excesses Which Led to the Communist Takeover", typescript drafts, April 14, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous holograph notes (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "The Political Situation Between the United States and China", typescript and photocopy of speech to the U.S. Naval Academy (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "The Significance of Discussions Between the United States and Red China", typescript of speech (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "A Tale of Three Cities", draft of Chapter I; "The Situation in China up to December, 1941, draft of Chapter II, n.d., December 7-8, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "This Fury", Prelude - page 269, typescript of novel, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - "This Fury", pages 270-890, typescript of novel, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - "Walkout", carbon copy of Frank Dorn's account of the Burma to India "walkout" by General Joseph W. Stilwell, his staff and others who were fleeing the advancing Japanese troops, pages 5, n.d., 1-27 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - "Walkout", pages 276-362, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes, research materials, lists for dictionary of the Negrito dialect, compiled by Frank Dorn while on duty in the Philippine Islands, ca. 1929 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - "Hungry Negritos in Their Watchful Forests", Asia, p. 72, November 1931 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Holograph and typescript notes by Frank Dorn (probably for use in Dorn's writings)
    - Chiang Mon-lin, Dr., March 8, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Condon, Col., interview, March 27, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Darrah, Col. J.W., letter, April 19, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, Col. Vann, May 7, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Kitts, Col. I.L., letter, March 16, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Kung, Mrs. H.H. (Soong Ai-ling), interview, March 9, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Middleton, Brig. Gen. J.W., letter, April 18, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Payne, Lt. Col. W.K., March 2, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Schwartz, Capt. March J., April 27, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Situation (Sino-American) in China", ca. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Stilwell, Gen. Joseph W., typescript, ca. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Sung Hsi-lien, Huo Kuei-chang, Huang Chieh, Chung Pin, Wang, Chou, Fang Tien, ca. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Ward, Col. Ivan W., letter, March 12, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Wedemeyer, Gen. Albert C., ca. 1945 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "After the Flag is Lowered", autobiography of Frank Dorn, ca. 1974
    - Preface, Part l (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Part 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Part 3 (Box 5, Folder 3-9)
    - Part 4 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Love and War at Pinatubo", photocopy, ca. 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "China in World War II, From Pearl Harbor to Tokyo Bay", 3 photocopies, letter of rejection, bibliography, ca. 1976, 1941-1945 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Subject File, 1932-1974
  Correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Chiang Kai-shek - Letter to Major General Wendell J. Coats from Frank Dorn noting contingency plans made during World War II for the assassination of Chiang Kai-shek, May 7, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - China-Burma-India Theater. Miscellaneous printed material (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kennedy, John F. Chinese poem copied by Frank Dorn on the death of Kennedy, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Peking, China. Guidebook, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Shanghai, China. International Settlement Incident between Japanese and American troops, Thermofax copies of correspondence and memoranda, April 29, 1932. (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Sino-Japanese relations. "The China Incident and Manchoukuo,", 1937 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Audio-Visual materials, 1926-1949 (Box 6, Box 7-9)
  1151 prints / 13 pencil drawings / 121 negatives / 24 postcards
  - 61 prints of Frank Dorn and others, Camp Sanchez, Philippine Islands; 63 prints of the Philippine Islands., 1926-29 (Box 7, Envelope A)
  - 147 prints of the Philippine Islands., 1929 (Box 7, Envelope B)
  - 128 prints of the Philippine Islands, including: 32 prints of Fort Stotsenburg; 32 prints of Yellow River Expedition; 31 prints of Northern Luzon., 1926-29 (Box 7, Envelope C)
  - 69 prints of Negrito tribesmen, Philippine Islands, circa 1929; 4 prints of scenes, Philippine Islands; 2 prints of maps of the Philippines, circa 1929. (Box 7, Envelope D)
  - 26 prints of Frank Dorn, 4 miscellaneous prints, Fort Sill, Oklahoma, 1931-1932; 6 prints of Oregon, 1 print of Frank Dorn, 1 miscellaneous print, 1933. (Box 8, Envelope E)
  - 4 prints of the Ming Tombs, Great Wall, China; 13 prints of Peking and environs; 5 prints of Potala, Jehol, China; 3 prints of the Temple of Heaven, Peking., 1934-1938 (Box 8, Envelope F)
  - 28 prints of Peking, 4 prints of Frank Dorn, 1935-1938; 9 prints of the Ming Tombs, 1935; 75 prints of Jehol, Dolunnor, Kalgan, 1935. (Box 8, Envelope G)
  - 3 prints of Suchow (Hsuchow Fu), China, 2 prints Lien Yung, China, 1935; 24 Scenic photos of Garden, 3 prints of Frank Dorn and Anna May Wong; 2 prints of Anna May Won; 2 prints of Frank Dorn and Mr. Mills, Peking, 1935-1936; 5 prints of T'ai Miao, Peking, 1936: 2 prints of Chou En-Lai, Hankow, China, 1938; 1 print of Frank Dorn; 7 prints of Frank Dorn and others, 3 prints of scenes in Shantung, China, 1937-38. (Box 8, Envelope H)
  - 13 prints of the Summer Palace, Peking, 1935-1938; 14 prints of Peking; 26 prints of the Western Hills with Frank Dorn and others, Peking; 1935-38; 4 scenes of China from book drawings; 7 miscellaneous prints of China; 8 prints of Japanese atrocities, 1937. (Box 8, Envelope I)
  - 6 prints of the Dowager Empress, Hze Hsi; 1 print of Emperor Hsuan T'ung (Pu Yi), circa 1922; 18 prints of China. (Box 8, Envelope J)
  - 62 prints of China; 7 prints of beheading in China, 1928. (Box 8, Envelope K)
  - 13 prints of China from books; 4 prints of China, 1936-38. (Box 8, Envelope L)
  - 1 print of Frank Dorn, Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, Frank Merrill; 4 prints of the China-Burma-India Theater during World War II; 2 unidentified prints; 2 prints of Gen. Wei Li-huang and Mrs. Wei., undated (Box 8, Envelope M)
  - 13 pencil drawings of the China-Burma-India Theater, World War II., undated (Box 8, Envelope N)
  - 8 prints of Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell and others; 3 prints of Frank Dorn and others, New Delhi, India, 1942; 1 print of Gen. Joseph W. Stilwell, 1 print of Gen Stilwell and others, New Delhi Airport after walkout from India, 1942; 1 print of Frank Dorn, John Davies; 1 print of Frank Dorn, Chou En-lai, Agnes Smedley; 1 print of Chou En-lai, 1 print of Fend Yu-hsiang; 1 print of Frank Dorn and others; 1 print of Frank Dorn, Gen. Stilwell and others in the China-Burma-India Theater, World War II. 4 prints of Chou En-lai; 2 prints of Chou En-lai, Frank Dorn, Agnes Smedley; 1 print of Chou En-lai and Frank Dorn; 1 print of Chou En-lai, Chu Teh, John P. Davies, Mao Tse-tung, Yeh Chien-ying; 2 print of Gen. Chiang Kai-shek and Mrs. Chiang, 1942. (Box 8, Envelope O)
  - 49 prints of Kunming headquarters and training centers., 1943-1945 (Box 8, Envelope P)
  - 1 print of Gen. Tu Li-ming; 1 print of Gen. Hsiao I-hsu; 1 print of Gen. Wei Li-huang., undated (Box 8, Envelope Q)
  - 29 prints of Walkout from Burma, 1942 (Box 9, Envelope R)
  - 59 prints of the Salween Campaign., 1944-45 (Box 9, Envelope S)
    Includes photographs of General Sunn Hsi-lien, Leitunant General Said I-su, General Chung Pin of the 71st Army, and General Chou Fu-cheng of the 53rd Army.
  - 9 prints of the Walkout from Burma., 1942 (Box 9, Envelope mT)
  - 56 prints of the Sino-Japanese War, 1937 (Box 9, Envelope mU)
  - 1 print of Chiang Kai-shek; 1 print of James Stewart and Frank Dorn; 1 print of Clare Boothe Luce and Frank Dorn; 1 print of General Stilwell's party walking out of Burma, 1942. (Folder mV)
  - 19 prints of Frank Dorn and others, 11th Airborne Division, Japan 1945; 3 prints of Frank Dorn and others, Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania, 1946-49., undated (Box 9, Envelope W)
  - 17 prints of Frank Dorn and others, Carlisle Barracks, Pa., 1948; 3 unidentified prints, Carlisle Barracks, Pa. (Box 9, Envelope X)
  - 1 print of Frank Dorn; 3 prints of Frank Dorn and others, 1952; 4 prints of atomic tests in Nevada, 1953; 1 print of Frank Dorn, Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower and others; 2 prints of Frank Dorn and others; 1 print of Frank Dorn, Lt. Gen. and Mrs. Clovis Byers, 1972. (Box 9, Envelope Y)
  - 12 prints of Austria' 17 postcards of Austria, 1947; 5 postcards of Borobodor, Java, 1938; 19 postcards of Bali, 1938-39. (Box 9, Envelope Z)
  - 119 negatives, undated (Box 9, Envelope AA)
  - 2 negatives of maps: Lower Burma Campaign; Upper Burma, General Joseph W. Stilwell's Route, April 25 - May 24, 1942. (Folder mBB)